A Guide to the Lynchburg (Va.) Chancery Causes, 1805-1945
Library of Virginia
- 1827-001: William Robertson and wife vs. Exr. of Robert Burton, etc. and Thomas Bowles and wife, etc. vs. Exr. of Robert Burton, etc.:
  Central question in this cause had to do with the status of two enslaved females, Jenetta and Myrtilla, that were part of Burton's estate. Jenetta was the wife of Thomas Bowles, a free African-American. The executor interpreted Burton's will as saying the enslaved women could hire themselves out to whomever they chose in order to support themselves until they married a free person. They would then receive a substantial legacy from Burton's estate. Moreover, they were to be emancipated as soon as the laws of the Commonwealth permitted it. The heirs of Burton did not agree with the executor's interpretation of Burton's will.
- 1827-023: Patsey Hawkins by c vs. William Hawkins:
  Separate maintenance cause. Multiple depositions and affidavits reference infidelity and spousal abuse both verbal and physical.
- 1827-037: John N. Rose vs. Hill Carter, etc.:
  John N. Rose sued the Carter family to recover wages owed to him for building an addition to the Carter home on Walnut Grove plantation in Nelson County in 1795. He built it for John Champe Carter and his wife Apphia. The reason the Carters gave for not paying Rose was that he never finished building the addition. Rose learned that the Carter family planned to auction eighty-eight enslaved people with proceeds from the sale to be divided among Carter family members. Rose wanted the court to have the Carters pay him what he was owed from the proceeds they receive from the sell of the enslaved people. Cause includes an inventory of enslaved people that list their names, age, and value. Unusual reference found in the deposition of Robert S. Rose. He was asked by the plaintiff if he knew Frank Floyd who was once owned by Robert's father and did he know what proportion of colored blood he has. Rose said that Frank was the son of Sarah Floyd who was the daughter of Betsey Dean, a mulatto. Her mother was black and her father was a white Englishman, an indentured servant to the deponent's grandfather. Sarah married a white man named Mitchel Floyd who died during the Revolutionary War.
- 1827-057: Lewis Wingfield vs. Hardin Hairston, etc.:
  Plaintiff and defendants were involved in tobacco trade. Cause details their efforts to sell tobacco in New York City and Charleston, SC.
- 1827-061: Louisa Cockrane alias Lavisa Cockrane vs. William Graves, etc.:
  Plaintiff was a free Afican American. She was suing to protect her property, land and a house, that she inherited from Richard Bennett, Sr.
- 1827-071: John Ward, Jr., etc. vs. Patsey Barbour, etc.:
  Cause involves the toll bridge across Staunton River. It references the destruction of the toll bridge in 1816 due to high water only months after it was completed.
- 1828-007: James Brownlee and wife vs. William Harlow, etc.:
  Cause involved a dispute related to the estate of Nathaniel Harlow. Brownlee was married to Harlow's daughter Susannah. He accused the defendants of denying his wife her fair share of her estate left to her in her father's will. The defendants' response was that Susannah was denied her portion of the estate because of her and Brownlee's bad character. They questioned the legitimacy of Susannah's marriage to Brownlee. At the time of their marriage, she was already married to James West who was still alive and resided in Kentucky. He was the son of an slaved person named Cillar. There are numerous depostions that attack Brownlee's character. Witnesses accused of him of murdering his first wife, being a drunkard, and operating a brothel out of his house in Waynesboro, Virginia. Witnesses describe Susannah as being "a large woman" who could not take care of herself. Brownlee hired people to assist him in taking care of her. Exhibits in the suit include Nathaniel Harlow's will, list of enslaved people owned by Harlow and their value, and James Brownlee and Susannah West's marriage certificate.
- 1828-015: John Cannaday vs. Cornelius Crow, etc.:
  Cause involves dispute over sale of enslaved people. The cause includes depositions and affidavits that detailed the health of an enslaved woman named Sally prior to when she was sold. She lost an infant child prior to being sold.
- 1828-037: Cornelius Powell vs. David S. Garland and David S. Garland vs. Cornelius Powell, etc.:
  Cause involves a disputed transaction of enslaved people. One was accused of attempting to poison her owner. The enslaved woman and her children were sold and taken out of the commonwealth to the "southern country."
- 1828-057: William Dickinson, Sr., etc. vs. Isaac Skillman, etc.:
  Cause involves an enslaved man named Randal or Randolph who was a blacksmith. He was hired out to work at an iron works in Botetourt County where other enslaved people were forced to labor. He was convicted of stealing and hung. The cause includes depositions and affidavits regarding Randal's character.
- 1828-070: James Veach and wife vs. Exr. of William Brown, etc.:
  Plaintiffs are free persons of color residing in the state of Ohio. Veach's wife was formerly Judith Brown. Her father's name was John Brown. The deceased defendant was her uncle who died in the burning of the theater in Richmond in 1811. Judith's grandfather and grandmother lived in Scotland.
- 1829-002: George Washington Taylor vs. Albon McDaniel, etc.:
  The defendants owned a shipping business that operated on the James River. They used enslaved people as boatmen and navigators.
- 1829-019: James Bullock, etc. vs. Achilles M. Haden:
  Plaintiff wanted the court to issue an injunction to prevent the defendant from removing an enslaved person from the Commonwealth. The defendant was a trader in enslaved people.
- 1829-035: Andrew Moreland vs. Elijah Fletcher, etc.:
  The plaintiff accused one of the defendants, Nancy Shields, of fraudulently hiring out an enslaved person to him. She knew the enslaved person suffered from the "King's Evil" or scrofula.